The value of personal experience is
worthless
if not reflected upon in the light of
God's goodness.
>> [applause]
>> And I'm not just saying keep a gratitude
journal.
Do that.
I got all kinds of little gratitude
tricks.
Me and Abby made one up on tour.
It's the best thing ever she showed me.
And I taught it on my YouTube channel.
And you can go there
and see it.
It's about a grateful heart is a stable
heart. I'm not just saying that. I'm
actually saying
things turn into blessings as you
reflect on them.
In time.
I will bless the Lord at all times.
Does that mean I'm going to walk down
the road singing Jireh this week?
Does that mean I'm going to be in a
meeting and they're going to be asking
about the spreadsheet and I'll be like,
"I don't know about the spreadsheet, but
my God is sovereign, he's holy, he's
righteous, he's pure. I bless him at all
times."
And it's like, "You can do that on your
own time. This is company time. We are
doing a meeting. Submit the budget." All
right. So, we're not turning
we're not turning this this
this beautiful Psalm into some
weird excuse for us to live in this
other reality. It actually is the way
that we bring God's faithfulness
into this moment for the fights that
you're dealing with
and for the future that you're uncertain
about.
And it's a beautiful thing.
It is a decision
that you make
to praise God,
to glorify him,
to speak about the things in your life
that you want to see more of.
To speak about the things in your life
that God has given you.
There's nothing wrong with admitting the
things that you wish were different and
getting help with them.
But stop elevating your request to
people who are not supervisors.
>> [applause]
>> What do you think I should tell my
husband? She's not married.
And even if she is, she is not married
to your husband.
She can only take you so far.
These conversations, they they get real
cyclical, right?
Cyclical.
Because in the process of that, if you
don't bring God into it, I'm talking
about delayed praise, and I'm going to
get back to that in just a moment, but
for now I want I want you to remember
this about David.
When he wrote Psalm 34, he was through
it.
When he was living it, and this may give
you permission to struggle a little bit.
That's why I called it ugly trust.
Because let me get out of the King
James, back over to the NIV, so you can
see what's going on in 1 Samuel 27,
verse 1.
But David
thought to himself,
"ONE OF THESE DAYS I WILL BE DESTROYED
BY THE HAND OF SAUL."
DOES THAT SOUND LIKE A GUY WHO'S
CONFIDENT IN GOD'S PROMISE?
But it's 7 years.
7 years IS LONG ENOUGH TO WHITTLE AWAY
AT your worship. And he thought TO
HIMSELF, "ONE OF THESE days I will be
destroyed by the HAND OF SAUL. THE BEST
THING I CAN DO,
the next BEST THING.
I DON'T LIKE WHAT I'VE GOT TO DO RIGHT
NOW. I DON'T LIKE WHERE LIFE HAS ME. I
DON'T LIKE THIS SITUATION. BUT THE BEST
THING I CAN DO CUZ I DON'T KNOW WHAT
ELSE TO DO, THE NEXT BEST THING, the one
thing I CAN DO CUZ GOD HAS TO HANDLE THE
NEXT THING AFTER that cuz I can't only
focus on one thing right now cuz I don't
really know about all this cuz it freaks
me out when I try to think too far out.
BUT THE BEST THING I CAN DO FOR NOW,
BACK PLEASE,
THE BEST THING I CAN DO IS ESCAPE TO THE
LAND OF THE PHILISTINES. THAT'S THE
ENEMIES.
THEN SAUL WILL GIVE UP SEARCHING for me
anywhere in Israel and I will slip out
of his hand. And David did that and for
16 months he lived amongst his enemies.
For 16 months he lived amongst the
enemies that he would eventually defeat
when he became king.
Hold that.
Hold that for a moment.
Go back to the very first part of that
verse. David thought to himself,
"I will bless the Lord at all times. His
praise will continually be in my mouth."
He thought to himself, "I'm going to
die."
But watch this. He said, "My soul will
make its boast in the Lord."
What's your soul?
Your soul is not your mouth.
Your soul is not what your eyes see.
Your soul is your mind, your will, and
your emotions. Put that in the comments.
Your mind, your will, your emotions.
Your mind, your will, your emotions. He
said, "My soul
will boast
in the Lord."
But we know that his mind was telling
him, "You're going to die.
You're not going to get through this.
This is it for you.
He's going to kill you for real this
time.
This is the end of the line.
This is where it stops. This is where
the fantasy ends. Yeah, that was cute
when Samuel anointed you when you were a
little boy. Samuel's dead now. Yeah,
that was cute when you saw your family
back together and happy again, but it's
not going to happen now. This is the
one. They used to have a show when I was
little called Sanford and Son, and he
would always say, "This is the big one,
Elizabeth. I'm coming to join you,
Elizabeth." What is up with all my
outdated pop culture references today?
Pray for me.
And David is having a moment. This is
it. He's going to kill me. This is it.
There's nothing else I can do. This is
the end. This is it. This one's going to
take me down. This is it. And he thought
that to himself, but he said, "My soul
is going to boast in the Lord,
and his praise will be in my mouth."
So,
his mind is saying one thing,
Saul's going to kill you.
But his soul
is going to say another thing,
I will
bless the Lord
at all times,
and his praise will continually be in my
mouth.
THE MOUTH IS GOING to say, "GOD IS
GOOD."
THE MOUTH IS GOING TO SAY, "GOD IS
GREAT."
MY MOUTH IS GOING TO SAY, "WHAT GOD
PROMISED,
HE WILL ACCOMPLISH."
MY MOUTH IS GOING TO SAY, "BUT HE'S
FAITHFUL, AND HE'S PROVEN THAT."
MY MOUTH WHAT I'M TRYING TO GIVE YOU IS
THIS SIMPLE PRINCIPLE. Give me my
camera. NOT EVERYTHING THAT GOES through
your mind needs to come out of your
mouth.
>> [applause]
>> YOUR MIND CAN TRY TO TELL YOU ALL THAT
YOUR MIND WANTS TO TELL YOU. OH, THIS IS
IT, BUT I DON'T WORSHIP MY THOUGHTS.
I DON'T EVEN TRUST THOUGHTS. I DON'T BOW
AT THE ALTAR OF MY THOUGHTS. THOUGHTS
ARE THOUGHTS, LIKE CLOUDS ARE CLOUDS,
LIKE RAIN IS RAIN. LET IT PASS OVER.
OKAY, DEVIL, YOU WANT TO TELL ME TO KILL
MYSELF? YOU CAN TELL ME THAT. I'M NOT
DOING THAT BECAUSE GOD HAS THE LAST WORD
IN MY LIFE. I'M [screaming] GOING TO
LIVE AND NOT DIE AND DECLARE THE
GOODNESS of the Lord in the land of the
living.
OPEN YOUR MOUTH [screaming]
AND SAY, "YES!"
YES, LORD!
>> [music]
>> YES, LORD, YES!
THAT'S WHY
>> [music]
>> HIGH FIVE SOMEBODY AND SAY, "I'M GOING
TO KEEP PRAISING HIM."
I'm going to keep praising him.
Even if I HAVE TO PRAISE HIM ON A DELAY.
WATCH THIS. HERE'S WHAT I MEAN, A
DELAYED PRAISE. DO YOU REMEMBER the
first time that you found out that live
TV wasn't really live?
You thought YOU WERE WATCHING LIVE TV
TILL SOMEBODY cussed and the TV just
went silent.
You remember the first time? I remember
the first time. I remember the first
time that I learned about the 7-second
delay.
That's what they use in TV. Now, we were
talking about 7 years, but let me shrink
this and make it real practical.
When they have a Super Bowl halftime
show
and things get exposed, you can Google
this later, that are not meant to be
exposed, the network cannot take the
liability that you just saw that on TV
cuz they got the FCC and the SEC and the
ACC and the Big Ten and all those the
all those Cs. And and and so they THEY
PUT IT ON A DELAY. WATCH THIS. SO, IN
CASE THEY NEED TO bleep it, they have
time. It was a 7-second
delay. THEY HAVE TO HAVE IT. THEY THEY
BROADCAST IT OUT 7 SECONDS AFTER IT
HAPPENS. And I'm trying TO FIGURE OUT,
DO I NEED TO put
a 7-second
delay?
>> [cheering]
>> Y'all getting quiet now. This sermon is
getting good. Do I need TO PUT A
7-SECOND delay from when it comes to my
mind
and when it comes OUT OF MY MOUTH?
SO, I CAN start bleeping some stuff
and censor myself
SO THAT I DON'T STAY STUCK IN WHAT I
FEEL, BUT MY SOUL CAN SPEAK AND SAY,
"NO. NO. NO. NO. NO, WE DON'T LIE DOWN
LIKE THAT. WE DON'T FIGHT BACK LIKE
THAT. WE DON'T GET NASTY LIKE THAT.
ARE YOU CRAZY?"
MY FRIEND WHO WORKS IN RADIO, HE SAID,
"IN RADIO, THEY CALL THAT THE DUMP
BUTTON."
I SAID, "WHAT IS THE DUMP BUTTON?" HE
SAID, "IF YOU SAY SOMETHING THAT YOU'RE
NOT SUPPOSED TO SAY LIVE ON THE AIR, YOU
GO, 'OOP.' YOU HIT A BUTTON AND IT TAKES
OUT THE LAST FEW SECONDS OF WHAT YOU
said
to protect the station from the
liability." I said to him, "They
[clears throat] have that in radio? Do
they have that in real life, too? CAN I
HAVE A DUMP BUTTON LIKE A LIVE DUMP
BUTTON IN MY LIFE? LIKE, YOU KNOW, LIKE,
you know, get a little sharp with
somebody, you don't mean to get sharp.
You say a little something that was
reserved and you're like, 'Oh, no, I
think that went out of thought
bubble-ville into like mouth
bubble-ville and I didn't know it
happened. Where's my dump button?"
This week,
>> [clears throat]
>> I want to I WANT TO CHALLENGE EVERYBODY
WHO IS STRUGGLING this week. You're not
struggling?
You could do it next week cuz you'll be
struggling then. You ain't perfect.
I want to challenge everybody who
struggles with magnifying the wrong
thing in your life.
Everybody who is struggling with how
you're speaking about this season, oh,
it's just a hard season. It's just a
horrible season. I know. I get it.
That season is called life on this
planet.
Now, tell who you need to tell.
>> [applause]
>> And I bring up Holly as a positive
example. I'm using her for an
illustration earlier. I'm using her for
going now. She did this last night. She
goes, "I just
I'm not going to say it."
AND SHE DIDN'T.
Y'ALL DON'T KNOW HER TO KNOW WHAT A
MIRACLE THAT WAS THAT SHE HIT THAT DUMP
BUTTON.
>> [cheering]
>> NOW, I KNEW I WAS PREACHING ABOUT THE
DUMP BUTTON. SHE DIDN'T.
SHE WAS GIVING ME A REAL LIFE
ILLUSTRATION
WHERE SHE WAS ABOUT TO CRITICIZE
SOMEBODY, but she wouldn't call it
criticism. No, we were praying for them.
BUT SOMETHING IN HER KNEW, THAT HOLY
GHOST SAID, THAT HOLLY HOLY GHOST SAID,
"ARE YOU REALLY PRAYING FOR them right
now?"
Can I get a dump button?
For the dumb stuff
that the devil tells me?
Can I put it even before my mouth? Can I
put it where it's like, "Oh, I'm not
going to think about that longer."
Can I put a 7-second rule on that? Like,
okay, we're going to worry about that
for 7 seconds. 7, 6, 5, 4. I wrote it
down. I didn't even need the last three.
You can have your 3 seconds back, devil.
I wrote it down. I put it there. I deal
with it later. Now, I'm going to do
this.
Wow.
David
found his dump button.
He knew to bring that stuff to God.
And to do the next best thing.
He knew
that there needs to be a delay
between what you feel. Oh, help me.
And what you do.
If you're thinking about going to see a
therapist soon for your problems, one
thing they're going to teach you that
I'll just give you for free and then you
can go on and see them and break it all
the way down. They're going to tell you
you need to put a bigger gap between the
thoughts and the feelings and the
actions.
So you can process and go like, is this
how I want to respond?
Or
a don't button.
As me and David like to call it.
I think it's important that we get this
because when he says his praise will
continually be in my mouth, that doesn't
mean that's everything that was going
through his mind.
>> [applause]
>> It was a
decision.
And I'mma give this personally cuz
somebody is going to be just for you.
The thing he was so afraid of
God was already lining up to take care
of it.
Let me think of that one. [applause]
The thing
that you are afraid of, God might
already be taking care of.
And
how much time do y'all have?
>> [cheering]
>> Okay.
Okay.
I make you promise. I will do at least
one
bonus teaching this week from the basin
on this subject.
And I will put it on my YouTube.
At least one.
I may need to do two.
It's so good.
Where did David go to escape from Saul?
To the land of the
Philistines.
Who was the first person that he
defeated that elevated him to a place of
prominence in front of the nation?
Goliath
from Gath who was an uncircumcised
Philistine.
Right?
You're like, uncircumcised? is that
really necessary to include that part?
It's in the Bible. I'm not bleeping
this, in the Bible.
When David eventually became king,
you got to get this.
He was the first one who delivered the
nation from the Philistines. And the
Bible says that he subdued those
enemies.
How did he do it?
What did David know
that Saul didn't that enabled him
to defeat the Philistines?
And when did he learn it?
I suggest
that in those 16 months
>> [snorts]
>> that he went to be a mercenary,
he was learning what time they ate
breakfast
and what time they went to bed.
David saw that 16 months
as a time where he was trapped.
God saw it as training.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> Can I tell you a time God did that to
me? When we started this church, there
were three different people, two of them
were ministries, one of them was an
individual, that said they were going to
pay my health insurance and my salary so
we could start the church cuz the church
didn't have
that many people. And they said, "We
don't want you to be burning yourself
out traveling and doing all this. We're
going to pay it." One by one, they all
backed out for different reasons. And no
no hard feelings toward them. But while
I felt having a little baby
cuz Elijah, my oldest, is the same age
as the church, and we had that baby and
we're moving. I remember and Chuck said,
"Well, we just need to step up and teach
people to trust God with the tithe and
build the church and trust God in this
area."
And I thought like, "Wow, is that is
that really what this is for?" And it
was it was.
If I had had those people do it for me,
I probably would have trusted them.
Who am I preaching to?
This is not about me. I'm I'm looking
for you.
>> [applause]
>> If if they did what I wanted them to do,
I wouldn't have seen what God can do.
And are you in a season right now? I'm
asking. Where God is teaching you to
trust. But it doesn't FEEL LIKE
TRAINING. IT feels like painting a
fence. IT DOESN'T FEEL LIKE TRAINING. IT
FEELS LIKE WAXING A CAR. I MIGHT AS WELL
FINISH OFF ALL MY references today. This
is my last shot to do it. IT DOESN'T
FEEL LIKE TRAINING, BUT IT IS. BUT YOU
DON'T KNOW THAT UNTIL YOU LOOK BACK ON
IT.
>> [applause]
>> YOU DON'T KNOW THAT WHILE IT'S
HAPPENING.
YOU DON'T KNOW THAT WHILE THEY'RE
SAYING, "I think we need to see other
people. It's not you, it's me. It's not
me, it's you." Whatever the thing is,
however however they say it, it still
hurts.
YOU DON'T KNOW AT THE TIME
THAT EVERYBODY SAY THAT.
THERE IS A THAT
THAT YOU DON'T KNOW ABOUT RIGHT NOW
THAT GOD DOES.
AND WHILE THE ENEMY IS TELLING YOU,
"YOU ARE NEVER GOING TO MAKE IT THROUGH
THIS."
And I DON'T EVEN KNOW WHAT YOUR THIS IS.
AND I WISH I DID, CUZ I WOULD SPEAK
STRAIGHT TO IT.
I WOULD CALL IT OUT BY NAME AND SOCIAL
security number.
IF I KNEW EXACTLY WHAT Y'ALL were
fighting about. If I knew exactly what
you were taking too many pills about. IF
I KNEW EXACTLY what you were asking God
for and feeling the silence of a prayer
that bounces back down and you keep
seeking but it keeps alluding you and it
keeps slipping away. I WOULD CALL IT BY
NAME. I DON'T KNOW WHAT YOUR THIS IS BUT
GOD DOES.
>> [applause]
>> BUT THERE'S SOMETHING ELSE YOU KNOW THAT
I WANT to remind you of today.
That you tend to forget IN MOMENTS LIKE
THIS.
WHERE YOU have tasted
the sting of your tears about the
situation THAT GOD WON'T CHANGE. WHERE
YOU HAVE TASTED THE AIR OF HUNGER FOR
THE RELATIONSHIPS THAT HAVE LEFT YOUR
LIFE.
>> [snorts]
>> A LOT OF TIMES WHILE THE ENEMY IS
SAYING, "YOU'RE NOT GOING TO GET THROUGH
THIS. What are you going TO DO ABOUT
THIS? HOW ARE YOU GOING TO HANDLE THIS?"
You forgot about
that.
>> [applause]
>> And you were singing about that.
You said, "That's why I trust him."
That's why.
Somebody shout, "That's why."
I want to all caps chat all caps that in
the chat right now from everybody. PUT A
THAT in the chat right now. Put a that
in the chat. And when you put it in the
chat, I want it to stand for this. T,
things. H, he already. T, taught.
Me.
>> [applause]
>> Don't mess up the acronym.
THINGS HE ALREADY TAUGHT THAT.
THINGS HE TAUGHT YOU
IN THE VALLEY
THAT YOU WENT THROUGH BEFORE THE
MOUNTAIN THAT WAS ON THE OTHER SIDE.
I'M TALKING ABOUT SEASONS WHEN YOU WERE
BROKE, BUT HE FED YOU LIKE A FATHER
FEEDS MANA TO HIS CHILDREN. THAT.
>> [applause]
>> YEAH, THAT.
THE THING THAT YOU PUSHED THROUGH AND
YOU DIDN'T EVEN KNOW YOU WERE THAT
STRONG. YOU FELT A LITTLE COCKY FOR 3
DAYS AFTERWARDS. YOU'RE LIKE, "OH, WOW.
HEY MAN, THAT WAS HARD, BUT I DID IT."
THAT.
YOU FORGET THAT EVERY TIME YOU GO
THROUGH THIS.
BUT TODAY'S
THIS [screaming]
IS JUST A THAT IN THE MAKING.
AND SO I CAME TO PREACH TODAY. GIVE ME 5
MINUTES, I'LL FINISH. THIS MESSAGE IS
ABOUT DELAYED PRAISE. WHAT ARE YOU
SAYING, PREACHER? I'M SAYING THANK HIM
TODAY FOR WHAT WILL ONLY MAKE SENSE
LATER. GIVE HIM A PRAISE RIGHT NOW FOR
WHAT YOU CAN'T POINT TO, FOR WHAT YOU
CAN'T PROVE, FOR WHAT YOU CAN'T
VERBALIZE, FOR WHAT YOU CAN'T
UNDERSTAND. PUT A PRAISE ON THAT, ON
THAT SITUATION, ON THAT
MISUNDERSTANDING,
ON THAT STEP, on that question, ON THAT
INTRICACY, ON THAT STRUGGLE, ON THAT
STRONGHOLD.
>> [music]
>> I'm not done yet. I'm not DONE YET CUZ
GOD SAID WE NEED TO GET YOU BACK TO
THAT.
YOU'RE GOING THROUGH THIS IS FINE, BUT
THAT'S NOT WHY YOU TRUST HIM. THAT'S NOT
WHY YOU PRAISE HIM. THAT'S NOT WHY YOU
LOVE HIM. YOU DON'T LOVE HIM CUZ IT'S
ALWAYS A FEELING. YOU LOVE HIM BECAUSE
HE FIRST LOVED YOU.
>> [applause and cheering]
>> You haven't BEEN WHO YOU WANT TO BE
LATELY. YOU'VE BEEN STRUGGLING WITH
PERFORMANCE ISSUES. THERE'S BEEN HEAVY
GUILT, HEAVY SHAME, HEAVY FEAR ON YOU.
WELL, IT'S A GOOD THING YOU'RE NOT
PRAISING HIM ACCORDING TO YOUR
PERFORMANCE.
YOU'RE PRAISING HIM ACCORDING TO HIS
GOODNESS.
>> [applause]
>> AND HE IS GOOD
AND ALL THE TIME
OH, TASTE AND SEE THAT THE LORD
[screaming] IS GOOD. I'M NOT PRAISING
HIM FOR THIS PAIN IN MY BODY. I'M NOT
PRAISING HIM FOR THIS ISSUE WITH MY
KIDS. I'M NOT PRAISING HIM FOR THIS
SITUATION THAT WILL RESOLVE. I'M
PRAISING HIM FOR THAT. YOU WANT TO GO
ALL THE WAY BACK? LET ME TAKE YOU TO
CALVARY WHERE THE PRECIOUS LAMB OF GOD
SUFFERED, BLED, AND DIED for me. SEE THE
CROWN OF THORNS ON HIS HEAD. SORROW AND
LOVE FLOW MINGLED DOWN. DID EVER SUCH
LOVE AND SORROW MEET? OR THORNS COMPOSE
SO RICH A CROWN? I'M NOT PRAISING HIM
FOR A FEELING. I'M PRAISING him by
faith. This is A FAITH PRAISE. I PRAISE
HIM LIKE THAT. I GOT IT
>> [music]
>> LIKE THAT. I KNOW IT LIKE THAT. I MET
HIM LIKE THAT. HE SNATCHED ME LIKE THAT.
HE FILLED ME LIKE THAT. HE RAISED ME
LIKE THAT. HE FORGAVE [music] ME LIKE
THAT. THAT'S WHY I
>> [screaming]
>> PRAISE.
HEY, thanks for [music] stopping by my
YouTube channel. I hope you were blessed
today. If you were, share this with
somebody. Like and subscribe and leave
me a comment. Let me know where you're
watching from, what [music] we can pray
for you about. Hope to see you back here
again really soon.